Guide to the Bert N. Corona Papers, 1923-1984
Department of Special Collections
Bert N. Corona Papers,
1923-1984
Special Collections M0248
Corona, Bert N. 1918-.
24 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Personal papers including correspondence; manuscripts; interviews; subject, alphabetical, and legal case files; newspapers; and photographs.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions on access.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Bert Corona, 1980 and 1986.
Biographical Note
Born in El Paso, Texas, in 1918, Corona joined the labor movement soon after his arrival in Los Angeles in 1936. He became a prominent organizer within the CIO, helping to organize Spanish-speaking workers in low-paying jobs. During the 1930s he was also involved in organizational work within the Mexican American community and, along with Luisa Moreno, Josefina Fierro, Eduardo Quevedo and others, he participated in El Congreso de Pueblos de Habla Española, one of the earliest Mexican American groups to address political concerns. During the 1940s, when animosity between the Los Angeles Police Department and the Mexican American community was growing, Corona was instrumental in defusing the tensions. He was active in the Citizens' Committee for te Defense of Mexican-American Youth (also known as the Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee) which represented the first organized effort led by Mexican Americans to resist police attacks on their community.
The 1950s were a quieter period for Corona, since the hysteria generated by Sen. Joseph McCarthy and the McCarran-Walter Acts made it difficult for political activists to function. Despite the period's conservatism and xenophobia, Corona continued to be politically active, serving as Regional Organizer for ANMA (National Association of Mexican-Americans), an organization formed in 1948 which fought to preserve the cultural heritage of Mexican Americans. As Regional Organizer, Corona spent a good amount of time traveling, organizing local chapters, and working with braceros, who were among the organizations strongest supporters.
When the Chicano movement emerged in the late 1960s, Corona was able to provide experienced leadership. He worked with organizations whose activities were strictly political, serving as President of the Mexican-American Political Association (MAPA) and encouraging the formation of an independent Chicano political party, La Raza Unida Party. At the same time Corona grew increasingly concerned with the welfare of undocumented Mexican workers who were less likely to participate openly in political organizations. Unhappy with the United Farm Workers policy towards the undocumented workers, he formed El Centro de Ayuda. Staffed by volunteers from various law firms, the center assisted workers with immigration problems, while at the same time encouraging the workers to organize. El Centro grew quickly and eventually changed its name to reflect its expanded functions, becoming the Centro de Acción Social Autónoma (CASA).
In addition to work on immigration policy, Corona has taught Chicano Studies at the California State University Los Angeles, where he worked for over a decade.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the Corona papers consists of files from his organizational work and course material for his Chicano Studies classes. The papers were sorted into subject files to give the collection dimension and to provide a key to the breadth of Corona's interests and activities. The papers are particularly strong in Mexican American political affairs and the international labor movement.
The first nine series are personal files that contain information specifically about Corona. Series II contains speeches and manuscripts for publication attributed to Corona, although it was frequently impossible to distinguish between a manuscript destined for publication and one that was presented at a meeting or lecture. Many manuscripts were used for several purposes. Series III, Correspondence, is mainly incoming letters and notices from organizations, arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization. Many letters were kept but never opened by Corona. This mail was opened and arranged because it reflected the many organizations with which Corona kept in touch and it was an indication of the scope of Mexican American political activities in the United States and other western countries.
Series X, (Subject Files), with sixteen sub-series, is the longest and most complex series. The files in this collection were gathered from several of his offices, including the files he kept at the various organizations where he worked, and his teaching files from the University of California at Los Angeles, and at Fullerton.
Chicano Studies (Sub-series M), contains material Corona used to prepare lectures and presentations for his classes at California State University at Los Angeles and at Fullerton. He also taught courses occasionally at Berkeley and at San Francisco State and other institutions. The multiple copies of articles found in this sub-series were assumed to be required reading materials for distribution to his students. In addition to reading material there are course descriptions, syllabi, bibliographies, flyers, campus notices and other information on immigration, labor issues, and related issues. Duplicates were kept only if they had unusual artistic or historical value.
The remaining subject headings are self-explanatory, except for Series X, Sub-series M: Student Papers. Corona kept many term papers and examination papers submitted by his students. All of the student papers were written for Corona's Chicano Studies Classes and are on topics related to the courses. The papers in this subseries were put in alphabetical order by title. A list of titles is in the Corona Collection File folder.
Files that did not fit into the major subjects, and those that bridge several headings, were alphabetized in Series XI. Lengthy folder titles should aid the researcher in finding useful primary material. The few photographs found in the collection form Series XII. Series XIII contains divorce case files and are closed temporarily because of the private nature of the files. A list of the litigants' names are in the Corona Collection file folder and are not included in this Guide.
Finally, Series XIV contains an impressive array of newspapers from all over the world. These are not complete runs of any series, but selected issues Corona kept, usually for the articles and information on immigration problems and labor action in many different countries.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Chavez, Cesar, 1927-.; Fierro, Josephina.; Sanchez, Robert.; Shibley, George.; Centro de Acción Social Autónomo, Hermandad General de Trabajadores.; Citizens Committee for the Defense of Mexican-American Youth.; Comité Nacional Organizacion Sindical de Trabajadores Immigrantes.; Hermandad Mexicana Nacional, Inc.; Mexican American Political Association.; National Committee against Repressive Legislation (U.S.); Partido Communista Mexicano. Comité Central.; United States. Immigration and Naturalization Service.; Partido Socialista Revolucionario (Mexico); United Farm Workers.; Nacozari mine strike.; Sleepy Lagoon Trial, Los Angeles, 1942-1943.; Los Angeles (Calif.).; Mexican American studies.
Container List
- Personal and Biographical Information, 1976-1979, Series 1
  This series contains resumes, 1979; an appointment Calendar, 1978; a teaching Certificate Application, 1977; and a tape recording, "Interview with Bert Corona about the status of his collection to be donated to Stanford," June 12, 1976.
  - Resumes, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appointment Calendar, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Teaching Certificate Application, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tape recording, Interview with Bert Corona about the status of his collection to be donated to Stanford, June 12, 1976[stored in box 54]
- Writings and Speeches by Bert Corona, 1969-1982, Series 2
  The series primarily contains speeches and writings written, presented, or co-authored by Bert Corona in both English and Spanish from 1969 through 1982. Includes copies of speeches given at various trade union meetings, political party meetings in both the United States and Mexico, and at various universities.
  - Address to the XVIII Congreso del PMC, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Analyzing the Writing of our History and its Importance, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Banquet '78: Committee for a New Immigration Policy, includes a manuscript [speech?] by Corona (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Carter Offers Mexico a Bracero (H-2) Program for It's (sic) Oil and Gas! What a Bargain??? for a conference in Tijuana, Mexico, September 8, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Chicano People: An Oppressed National Minority, in New Generation, Fall, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Las Condiciones de los Trabajadores Inmigrantes en Estados Unidos, por Bert Corona, Secretario de National Trade Union Organizing, [speech for Conferencia Sobre Inmigración, San Francisco], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bert Corona Speaks on La Raza Unida Party & the `Illegal Alien' Scare, pamphlet (first published in The Militant, April 7 and April 28, 1972,Pathfinder Press, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - In Defense of the Mexican Workers Without Visas in the United States, (in Spanish and English) World Federation of Trade Unions, 9th Congress, Prague, Czechoslovakia, April 16-24, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Economic Effects of Immigration from Mexico into the U.S.A., speech and references used, ca. 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Una Historia de la Politica de Inmigración de los Estados Unidos de Norte America, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Income, Jobs and Job Training and the Chicano Community in the San Fernando Valley, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Inmigración en EU, Analisis de la Ley Eilberg, por Bert Corona, Excelsior, 13 de Enero de 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Manuscripts by Bert Corona (4), no title, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - MAPA and La Raza Unida Party, A Program for Chicano Political Action for the 1970s, 1970? (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Mexican People in the United States of North America, an Outline, by Bert Corona, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Mexican Scholars and Public Issues in the U.S.A. in the 80s, speech before NACHS, Phoenix, Arizona, March 28, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - `The Mexican Worker in the Building of the American Labor Movement,' bibliography for paper by Bert N. Corona, Professor CSULA, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Luisa Moreno: Labor Leader Deported for her Success, article, contributed to by Bert Corona, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Must the Immigrant Worker be the Scapegoat for the Crisis, by Bert Corona, World Trade Union Movement, April 1974 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - El Plan Carter: Un Juego Peligroso de Propuestas Legislativas, for Conferencia Culiacan, Universidad Autónoma de Sinaloa, México, June 20, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Political Perspectives for the Chicano Communities in the U.S.A. for the Decade of the 80's by Bert N. Corona, August 20, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Primer Simposium Sobre Las Causas y Los Efectos De La Migración En México y Los Estados Unidos at the Universidad Autónoma De Sinaloa, clippings, June 16-20, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Primer Simposium Sobre Las Causas y Los Efectos De La Migración En México y Los Estados Unidos, includes Corona's Speech, program, and poster, June 16-10, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Primer Simposium Sobre Las Causas y Los Efectos De La Migración En México y Los Estados Unidos, (13) papers presented at the Symposium, June 16-20, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Problemas de Inmigración, Derechos Humanos y Laborales y Relaciones Mexico-Estadounidenses, by Humberto N. Corona, Septiembre 24, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Que es Casa? by Bert Corona in Prensa Popular, June 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Questions Asked by Bert Corona to the Gubernatorial Candidates and U.S. Senatorial Candidates at the State of California Democratic Issues and Candidates Conference, Fresno City Convention Center, November 8, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Role of the Mexican Immigrant Worker in the Labor Force of the State of California from 1924 to 1980, testimony before the Select Commission on Immmigration and Refugee Policy, February 4, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Scapegoating, May 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Untitled editorial, César Chavez once aptly called `La Migra' `The Gestapo of the Mexican People of the United States...,' 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Untitled speech, Farm workers in the United States whose struggle for justice began more than 100 years ago,..., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Untitled speech, We in the Hispanic Community that comprises some 20,000,000 people in this nation..., Atlanta, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Untitled 3 minute radio spot, Les Habla César Chavez con un mensaje de suma importancia para todos nostros Mexicanos demas de habla española..., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - What Has Been the Historical Relationship Between Labor and Chicano Politics? by Bert Corona, SOMOS, December 1978/January 1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Why Labor and La Raza Should Break With the Republican and Democratic Parities, speech at the Mi Raza Primero Conference in Muskegon, Michigan, January 22, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Workers Without Visas, by Lorenzo Torres and Humberto Corona, World Trade Union Movement, February 1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1963-1980, Series 3
  This series contains copies of outgoing correspondence from 1963 - 1980, as well as copies of incoming correspondence from roughly the same time period arranged alphabetically by the sender.
  - Out-going, 1963-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Out-going, CASA, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Out-going, Comité Nacional Organización Sindical de Trabajadores Inmigrantes, 1975-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - In-coming from organizations, A-B (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - In-coming from organizations, C (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - In-coming from organizations, D-G (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - In-coming from organizations, H-M (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - In-coming from organizations, N-R (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - In-coming from organizations, S-Z (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - In-coming from individuals, A-G (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - In-coming from individuals, H-M (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - In-coming from individuals, N-R (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - In-coming from individuals, S-Z (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence from César Chavez and the United Farm Workers, 1973-1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Letters from students, ca. 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notary correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Articles about Corona, 1967-1983, Series 4
  This series contains articles about Corona that appear in various Spanish language newspapers, the Congressional Record, and University Times, a periodical put out by the California State University of Los Angeles.
  - Congressman McDonald attacks Bert Corona, Congressional Record, June 18, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bert Corona Habla de los Oprimidos de Aquí y de Alla, El Sol de Sinola, August 25, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bert Corona Habla Sobre Proyecto de Inmigración, Semanario Azteca, August 31, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Bert Corona Reinstated to Teach `Without Conditions,' University Times, CSULA, October 13, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Corona Hits Rodino-Kennedy Bill, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Llamado de la Iglesia en Favor de Indocumentados Salvadoreños, El Mexicano, Baja California, Mexico, Noviembre 25, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Nava Rejection Angers Hispanic Community, University Times, CSULA, May 30, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Neighbors or Aliens? by Gregory Bergman, extensive quotes from Bert Corona, April 1980 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - El Popo, issue dedicated to Bert Corona, vol. 7, no. 4, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Professor Planning to File Suit Against Administration, University Times, CSULA, September 29, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Three Professors Speak Out Against Campus Arrests; Lawsuit to be Filed Today, University Times, CSULA, June 3, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Untitled Speech about Corona, We are gathered here to honor [Bert Corona]..., by Manuel Ortiz, Student Body President, Imola, California, June 30, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Wilmington Coordinating Council, Wilmington, California, minutes with summary outline of Corona's invited speech at their meeting April 13, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Interviews with Corona, 1980, Series 5
  This series contains an interview with Corona as well as information about requests for interviews with him.
  - An interview with Bert Corona, Western Journal of Speech Communication, Summer 1980 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Requests for interviews, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Documentaries about Corona, n.d., Series 6
  This series contains the script for a documentary about Bert N. Corona.
  - Achieving Goals Series, Bert Corona, Community Organizer, script, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Invitations for Corona to Speak, 1963-1982, Series 7
  This series contains letters about speaking engagements to which Bert N. Corona had been invited to participate.
  - Letters re: speaking engagements, 1963, 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Letters re: speaking engagements, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Letters re: speaking engagements, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Letters re: speaking engagements, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Messages and Letters re: speaking engagements, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Messages and Letters re: speaking engagements, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Legal Action against Corona, 1977, Series 8
  This series contains a copy of a legal document in which Bert N. Corona claimed exemption from garnishment of wages.
  - Louis Herlick, et al. v. Bert N. Corona, Declaration of Bert N. Corona claiming exemption from execution [of garnishment of wages], January 14, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Endorsement, 1981, Series 9
  This series contains a press release in which Bert N. Corona supported Murv Glass for a position on the City Council.
  - Murv Glass for City Council, press release, September 1, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Subject files, 1923-1983, Series 10
  This series contains Bert N. Corona's extensive subject files on Chicano Studies, environmental issues, immigration, international issues, journals, labor issues, legal defense and lawyers associations, Mexican American issues, the Nacozari Mine Strike, peace organizations, political theory, prison issues, student papers, United States political campaigns and issues, urban problems, and women's issues.
  - CHICANO STUDIES MATERIALS, 1950s-1983, Sub-series 10.A
    - Bibliography, Immigration and the Mexican, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Bibliography, San Diego State College, Immigration Procedures and Practices, by Corona, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Bibliography, San Fernando Valley State College Library, September 1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Braceros, papers and clippings, 1950s to 1970s (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - California State University, Fullerton, class rosters, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - California State University, Fullerton, class rosters, course outlines, 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - California State University, Fullerton, clippings, syllabus, program Conference on History, Culture and Current Problems of Chicanos, April 9-10, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - California State University, Fullerton, course listing, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - California State University, at Fullerton and Los Angeles, flyers and memoranda, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - California State University, at Fullerton and Los Angeles, flyers and memoranda, 1977-1983 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, charges of racism, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, Chicano Studies, correspondence, telephone directory, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, Chicano Studies 490 Immigration, roster, lecture notes, course outlines, reading list, 1975, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, class rosters, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, class roster and faculty notices, 1974, 1975, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, class roster and faculty notices, 1974, 1975, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, class roster, flyers, clippings and memoranda, 1975-1981 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, contract for teaching, October 27, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, Course Material Chicano and Mexican People as Immigrants in the USA, Chicano Studies 405, by Carlos Vasquez, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, flyers, clippings, brochures, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, memoranda, clippings, faculty political issues, 1977-1983 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, memoranda, clippings, faculty political issues, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, memoranda, clippings, faculty political issues, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - California State University, Los Angeles, memoranda, clippings, faculty political issues, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - California State University, Northridge, Anti-Draft Counseling, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - California State University, Northridge, unemployment insurance appeals, July 30, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Cerritos College, program, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - The Chicano and Mexican People as Immigrants, Chicano Studies 191, Berkeley, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Chicano Studies, proposal by Ernesto Lucero, Instituto Michoacano de Planificacion, a.c., Morelia, Michoacan, Mexico, 1974-1976 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Chicano Studies, various California campuses, clippings and flyers, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Chicano Studies, various California campuses, records and flyers, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Civil Rights Digest, a Quarterly of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, Busing in Boston, Winter, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Consejo de Estudios Chicanos, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Course proposals for Mexican-American and Chicano Studies, various instructors, various schools, 1975, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - El Cowboy Norte Americano en El Folklore y La Literatura, by Americo Paredes, The University of Texas Institute of Latin American Studies Offprint Series, No.22, reprinted from Cuadernos del Instituto Nacional de Antropologia, Buenos Aires, No. 4, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Education and the Vato Loco, by Richard Abrams, (7) pages, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Educational issues for Chicano and Mexican-American students: Compton School District, Mexican-American Studies, education in correctional institutions, 1969-1970. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Encuesta sobre las Opiniones y Características que Sostiene El Pueblo Mexicano o de Habla Española en el Condado de Los Angeles, California en 1980; Asuntos Económicos, Sociales y Políticos que Existen en los Barrios, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Hispanic Heritage Week: Faces of Progress, A Comprehensive Guide to Events Commemorating Hispanic Heritage Week in Los Angeles, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - History, Culture and Society: Chicano Studies in the 1980s, includes Chicano Scholars and Public Issues in the United States in the Eighties, by Bert Corona [for a copy with an earlier title Mexican Scholars and Public Issues in the U.S.A. in the 80s, a speech given at the National Association for Chicano Studies, 1982,see Series: CORONA, SPEECHES], 1982 (Box 7, Folder 11)